Ghent University Campus Tweekerken Tweekerkenstraat 2 BE-9000 Ghent *⋒* +32 495 364780 ⊠ rubenL.dewitte@ugent.be www.rubendewitte.be

Dr. Ruben Dewitte

Economist and teacher with nine years of experience researching the micro-foundations of macroeconomic models to address policy-relevant questions related to international trade, labor and product market power, environmental policy, productivity, technological change, innovation, aggregate volatility, and economic growth. Strong data skills working with large firm-level datasets. Coordinated and led multiple research projects, which have been published in leading economic journals such as the Journal of Political Economy, the Journal of Applied Econometrics, the European Journal of Operational Research, and the Canadian Journal of Economics. Collaborated with research experts from academia, national banks, and public institutions. Successfully contributed to competitive funding applications and presented at international conferences. Trained and supervised PhD and master students. Hold a Ph.D. in economics from Ghent University and research master in economics from Université catholique de Louvain.

Current Positions

2022-current **Visiting professor**, *Ghent University*, Ghent

2021-current Postdoctoral research fellow of Research Foundation Flanders (FWO), Ghent *University*, Ghent

> As a postdoctoral researcher and visiting professor, I divide my time between fundamental research in line with my research interests and teaching. My teaching tasks are listed below.

- Responsible lecturer for the course 'International Trade and Migration' (6 ECTS) in the 'Master of Science in Economics';
- o Co-lecturer for the course 'European Economic Integration and Regional Integration Analysis' (9 ECTS) in the Master 'Economics of Globalization and European Integration';
- o Consultant for the international economics seminar (6 ECTS across three seminars) in which third-year economic bachelor students learn to analyze the impact of recent trade agreements;
- Supervisor of master dissertations (18-24 ECTS).

Previous Positions

2021 **Research intern**, National Bank of Belgium, Brussels

Research internship granted for the research project 'Identifying Latent Heterogeneity in Productivity' that was published as NBB Working Paper no. 428 in 2022.

2020–2021 **Postdoctoral researcher**, *Ghent University*, Ghent

As a postdoctoral researcher, I continued developing my research agenda while providing teaching support. My teaching tasks are listed below.

- o Co-lecturer for the course 'European Economic Integration and Regional Integration Analysis' in the Master 'Economics of Globalization and European Integration' (9 ECTS);
- o Lecturer of Gravity in Economics class during the 'Trade and Migration Policy' course (6 ECTS) in the 'Master of Science in Economics':
- Responsible for the international economics seminar (6 ECTS across three seminars) in which third-year economic bachelor students learn to analyze the impact of recent trade agreements;
- Supervisor of master dissertations (18-24 ECTS);
- Help coordinate the UN simulation game in the bachelor course 'Economic Globalization'.

2014–2020 **Teaching assistant**, *Ghent University*, Ghent

As a teaching assistant, I worked on my PhD thesis titled "Firm Heterogeneity in International Trade" under the guidance of Prof. Dr. Glenn Rayp while providing teaching support. My teaching tasks are listed below.

- Responsible for the international economics seminar (6 ECTS across three seminars) in which third-year economic bachelor students learn to analyze the impact of recent trade
- o Assist Prof. Dr. Glenn Rayp and Prof. Dr. Ilse Ruyssen with their master course 'Modern Trade and Migration Policy' and bachelor courses 'International Economics', 'Economic Globalization' and 'Development of Economic Science';
- Assist with the exercise sessions of the first-year general economics course.

Grants and Funding

- 2023–2024 National Bank of Belgium's MiRDH pilot phase, 'Identifying firm-level markup variation across firms and over time without prices', Data and server access with value < 10,000 EUR
- 2021–2024 Postdoctoral research fellowship at Research Foundation Flanders (FWO), Grant 12B8822N, \pm 250,000 EUR
- 2021-2024 National Bank of Belgium Research top-up grant junior post-doc, FWO21/PDJ/092, \pm 30,000 EUR
 - 2021 **NBB Research internship**, 'Identifying Unobserved Heterogeneity in Productivity', < 10,000 EUR

Education

2015–2020 **Doctor of Economics**, *Ghent University*, Ghent, No grade

Thesis title: Firm Heterogeneity in International Trade.

Supervisor: Glenn Rayp

Examination committee: Gerdie Everaert, Bruno Merlevede, Luca David Opromolla, Gonzague

Vannoorenberghe, Marijn Verschelde

2014–2015 Master in General Economics: Research Focus, Université Catholique de Louvain, Louvain-la-Neuve, Distinction

> Thesis title: Comparative advantage and heterogeneous firms. The case of Portugal. Note: This master was followed to prepare for the Ph.D. program at Ghent University and was obtained while active as a teaching assistant at Ghent University.

2013–2014 Master of Science in Economics, Ghent University, Ghent, Great Distinction Thesis title: Middle-income trap and export sophistication. Assessment and economic policy implications.

- 2012–2013 Erasmus Exchange Program, Université de Neuchâtel, Neuchâtel
- 2010–2013 **Bachelor of Science in Economics**, *Ghent University*, Ghent, *Great Distinction* Thesis title: *Measuring human well-being based on an idea of Robert H. Frank.*

Single Courses

spring 2017 Research on Productivity, Trade, and Growth: Theory and Practice, *Tinbergen Institute*, Amsterdam, No grade

This course focused on empirical research using firm-level data. It introduced dynamic firm models, productivity estimation techniques, and structural modeling of productivity, trade, and growth. It was taught by Prof. Dr. Eric Bartelsman, Prof. Dr. Jan de Loecker and Prof. Dr. Jo Van Biesebroeck.

- spring 2017 **Economic Growth**, *Kiel Institute for The World Economy*, Kiel, Greatest distinction This course was part of the 2017 'Advanced Studies in International Economic Policy Research'-program. It was taught by Prof. Dr. Gino Gancia and focused on topics in the area of economic growth and technological progress.
- spring 2017 **Resampling methods with applications**, *Université Catholique de Louvain*, Louvain-la-Neuve, Greatest Distinction

This course was part of the 'Master in Statistics'-program. It was taught by Prof. Dr. Germain Van Bever and focused on the theoretical properties of resampling methods and their applications that are useful in statistics and econometrics.

fall 2016 **Non- and semi-parametric econometrics**, *Université Catholique de Louvain*, Louvain-la-Neuve, Distinction

This course was part of the 'Master in Statistics'-program. It was taught by Prof. Dr. Christian Hafner and focused on non- and semi-parametric estimation methods that are often used in econometrics.

Refereed Publications

Ruben Dewitte, Bruno Merlevede, and Glenn Rayp, Accepted at the *Journal of Applied Econometrics*. Gains From Trade: Demand, Supply and Idiosyncratic Shocks.

Ruben Dewitte, The Gravity Equation in International Trade: A Note., *Journal of Political economy*, 130(5), 1412-1418.

Ruben Dewitte, Michel Dumont, Glenn Rayp, and Peter Willemé, 2022. Unobserved Heterogeneity in the Productivity Distribution and Gains From Trade., *Canadian Journal of Economics*, 55(3), 1566-1597.

Ruben Dewitte, Michel Dumont, Bruno Merlevede, Glenn Rayp and Marijn Verschelde, 2020. Firm-Heterogeneous Biased Technological Change: A nonparametric approach under endogeneity., *European Journal of Operational Research 283(3)*, 1172–1182.

Work in Progress

Ruben Dewitte, Catherine Fuss, and Angelos Theodorakopoulos, NBB working paper no. 428. Identifying Latent Heterogeneity in Productivity.

Ruben Dewitte, Work in Progress. From Heavy-Tailed Micro to Macro: on the characterization of firm-level heterogeneity and its aggregation properties.

Ruben Dewitte, Work in Progress. The Log of Heavy-Tailed Gravity.

Ruben Dewitte, Giorgio Presidente, and Angelos Theodorakopoulos, Work in Progress. Technology, Prices, and Market Power.

Ruben Dewitte, Simon Happersberger, Nidhi Nagabhatla, Glenn Rayp, and Linh Bui Thi Thuy, Work in Progress. The Design of Environmental Impact Assessments of Trade Agreements.

Conferences, Workshops & Seminar Presentations

- 2023 ITIM seminar (Ghent, March), ETSG (Guildford, September)
- 2022 Antwerp University Job Market Seminar (Antwerp, January), BORDERS workshop (Ghent, March), CEA (Ottawa, June), ETSG (Groningen, September)
- 2021 ITIM seminar (Ghent, February), CEA (online, June), vNAPW (online, June), ETSG (Ghent, September)
- 2019 Workshop on 'Firm heterogeneity in Technical Change' (Ghent, March), DEGIT XXIV (Odense, August), ETSG (Bern, September)
- 2018 Ghent University PhD day (Ghent, May), NAPW (Miami, June), CompNet (Halle, June), ETSG (Warsaw, September)
- 2017 Ugent General Economics Department meetings (Oudenaarde, May), Ghent University PhD day (Ghent, May), RIEF (Lille, June), ETSG (Florence, September).
- 2016 SNDE (Alabama, March), Ghent University PhD day (Ghent, May), Economics of Global Interactions (Bari, September), ETSG (Helsinki, September), Doctoral Workshop in Economics (Namur, December)
- 2015 Internal Seminar (Ghent, May)

Refereeing

European Economic Review, Economic Inquiry, Journal of Productivity Analysis, Empirical Economics, Applied Economics

Administrative Responsibilities

2021-current Coordination of the ITIM Seminars at Ghent University, Department of Economics.

2016-2018 Coordination (together with Sümeyra Atmaca) of the External Economics Seminars at Ghent University, Department of Economics.

Computer skills

R, Git, STATA, Matlab, Fortran, SPSS, Eviews

Languages

Dutch Native proficiency

English Full professional proficiency

French Professional proficiency

Spanish Elementary proficiency

References

Prof. Dr. Bruno Merlevede, Ghent University, bruno.merlevede@ugent.be

Prof. Dr. Glenn Rayp, Ghent University, glenn.rayp@ugent.be

Prof. Dr. Gonzague Vannoorenberghe, *Université catholique de Louvain*, gonzague.vannoorenberghe@uclouvain.be

Prof. Dr. Marijn Verschelde, IÉSEG School of Management, m.verschelde@ieseg.fr